finding the right pair of weighted
plates for your home gym can be a bit of
a daunting task since you have to think
about the style of lifts you're hitting
as well as how much money you can
comfortably spend bumper plates and
metal plates are pretty different so
which style should you go with well
that's why I'm here my friends so let's
go ahead and get right down to it
[Music]
yo what's up everybody it's Jake back in
the barbing garage gym with another
comparison review ready to go for you
all today this time I'm going to be
comparing bumper plates to metal plates
and help you decide which ones need to
be in your home gym but before I get
going with any of that I gotta let you
know we've reviewed a ton of weight
plates on barbin.com and if you want to
browse our best list just go and search
bar Bend best weight plates and you can
find out for yourself which ones are
going to suit your needs the best
foreign okay so let's talk about the
similarities between bumper plates and
metal plates now believe it or not
bumper plates are not all made of 100
rubber most of the time they're going to
feature some type of insert whether that
be steel or iron so there is a
similarity with both of these and the
fact that there is going to be some type
of metal used in some way shape or form
let's talk about weight now some
companies May opt for some different
weight options but the majority of
companies are going to stick with that
traditional 5 10 15 25 35 and 45 pound
weight options for you to work with this
goes for both bumper plates and metal
plates alike now in terms of function to
an extent there is a lot of similarities
between these style of plates and how
they're used when it's all said and done
I mean you're going to be using a weight
plate with a barbell now how you use
that barbell well that's going to depend
on which style of plate you go with so
let's go and transition into some
differences now
all right so for starters bumper plates
tend to be more expensive than metal
plates this is due to that added layer
of rubber it's going to add to the
lifespan it's going to add on to that
price as well metal plates tend to be a
little bit thinner than bumper plates
are that way you can really you know
load up a lot of weight on your barbell
and metal plates are also a lot noisier
than bumper plates are so they don't
absorb shock as well as bumper plates do
either so you really don't want to be
doing any Olympic style lifts because
you definitely are on the risk of
ruining your barbell at a much quicker
rate than you would with some bumper
plates metal plates also tend to have a
smaller diameter with the lower weight
options while with bumper plates their
diameters are pretty much always uniform
but the thickness is going to vary
depending on which weight option you're
using so just for example a 10 pound
bumper plate is going to have the same
diameter as a 45 pound bumper plate but
they're going to be much thinner bumper
plates are also designed to be dropped
here hearing overhead style lifts
Olympic lifts Crossfit style lists
really whatever it may be the rubber
coating is going to absorb the shock and
protect the barbell while that's
something you definitely don't want to
do with metal plates you really just
want to use these from a racked position
or maybe you know during a deadlift
where you can safely ease that weight
onto the ground
[Applause]
okay so let's talk a little bit about
some money now for the sake of this
video you know I'm going to be
discussing you know these deep dish
plates from Rogue and these Rogue Echo
bumpers now you head over to their
website you'll find that both of these
options right here are some of the more
affordable options that Rogue actually
has to offer now when it comes to these
45 pound pair of deep dish plates
they're priced around 180 bucks while
these broke Echo bumpers they're about
190 dollars that's going to be the case
with all the other weight options as
well you will be spending more money
with the bumpers if that's not enough
for you though let's go ahead and
compare their Olympic style plates to
their competition bumpers so a 45 pound
pair of the Olympic style plates they're
going to run you about 240 bucks off 45
pound pair of the competition bumpers
are about 330 dollars and you know this
isn't just the case with Rogue this is
going to be with all the other companies
out there as well bumper plates are just
going to cost you more money so if if
you want to save some money and you're
not really interested in doing some
Olympic style lifts like a power clean
or a hang clean you know anything like
that you're probably gonna be better off
saving some money and going after some
metal plates but remember they
definitely have a higher risk of rust
forming
all right guys so let's do a little bit
of a different walk around than I
typically do now I've got both of these
plates loaded up on a barbell right now
they're different barbells for different
reasons right so I've got these metal
plates on this power bar right here
that's typically what you're going to be
using with some metal plates because
most likely you know you're just
sticking to those big three powerless
you know squat bench and a deadlift
that's because you know you can load on
more weight with it which with metal
plates you're probably going to be
throwing on a whole lot of weight so
that barbell is going to be stronger and
you don't really need the versatility
like you would with this Olympic Bar
down here where you know the knurling is
better on your hands and the sleeves
spin that way you know you can do those
Olympic style lifts in any other lift
really where the barbell is going to be
dropped on the ground you know these
bumper plates are going to be really
beneficial for that because it's going
to protect the barbell and absorb that
shock it's going to keep any harm from
happening to it well you know with metal
plates
it's not the case it's not going to be
absorbing that shock it's all going to
be shared and really you know it's going
to put too much stress in the barbell
and it can actually you know break it
bend it whatever it may be a lot faster
than it would with some bumper plates
[Music]
okay so which style of plates should you
buy well this is going to be completely
based on whatever style of workouts that
you do so if you're a power lifter
focusing on the big three which is you
know squat bench and deadlift then you
don't really need added protection that
bumper plates provide so I would
definitely suggest going after some
metal plates however if you do want to
work in some power cleans or any other
Olympic and Crossfit style lift and you
absolutely want to snag yourself some
bumpers that way you're not ruining your
barbell and you know you're not that
neighbor
at the end of the day though you also
have to factor in money so you know if
you're on a tight budget you don't want
to spend you know some of your
hard-earned cash then you're definitely
going to be better off going with some
metal plates because they are cheaper
well that's all I have for you guys
today on this comparison between bumper
plates and metal plates these are two
completely different style of plates
designed for completely different styles
of workouts so to figure out your best
fit you just need to focus on what is
going to match your style the best
thanks for watching everybody I hope
this video was helpful and I was able to
make things a little bit easier for you
as you go to add some new plates to your
home gym as always stay on the lookout
for my next video but for now head over
to barbin.com and you can read more
about this comparison just search bar
Bend bumper plates first metal plates
you'll find everything I talked about
here today and I'll see y'all later
foreign
[Music]